A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Energy Policy Project Files FA539
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Energy Policy Project Files
1972-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA539
11.42 Cubic Feet 8 record storage boxes, 2 legal document boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged in 4 series:
1. Chronological Correspondence.
2. Speeches, Meetings and Testimony.
3. Subject Files.
4. Legal size.
Scope and Contents
Primarily contains correspondence, documentation of meetings and events and subject files.
Biographical / Historical
The Energy Policy Project (EPP) was a Ford Foundation Delegated Authority Project (DAP) that sought to research and analyze energy policy. The EPP lasted from 1972 to 1975, and in 1974, published its final report, A Time to Choose: America's Energy Future. In addition to the final report, the EPP published 19 project studies. The Foundation spent $4,150,000 for the project. Ford Foundation Resources and Environment Program Officer Edward Ames managed the project within the Foundation, and S. David Freeman was appointed as project director. Freeman had previously worked in the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), and after his leadership of the EPP, he was appointed chairman of the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) by President Jimmy Carter in 1978 and later held leadership positions in public utilities corporations like the New York Power Authority and the Los Angeles Department of Water and Power.
The EPP originated from a proposal the Ford Foundation Resources and Environment Program made for a program of energy studies in 1971. The Foundation's interest in the energy field preceded the EPP. It had made several energy related grants between 1968 and 1971. The EPP was active during the 1973 oil crisis, and as an independent group in Washington D.C. concerned with energy policy alternatives, it played an educational and advisory role to Congress, parts of the Executive branch, and various public interest groups.
Chief criticisms of the EPP and its A Time to Choose report centered around arguments about lack of objectivity and low quality analysis (An Evaluation of the Energy Policy Project, September 1975, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286 (FA739C), Report 006648).
- Chronological Correspondence, 1972-1974; I
  - Chrons, 1972 April 6-May 31 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 June 1-16 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 June 17-30 (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 July (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 August (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 September (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 October (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 November (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 December (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1972 December (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1973 January (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1973 January (Box 2)
  - Chrons (1/2), 1973 February (Box 2)
  - Chrons (2/2), 1973 February (Box 2)
  - Chrons (1/2), 1973 March (Box 2)
  - Chrons (2/2), 1973 March (Box 2)
  - Chrons (1/2), 1973 April (Box 2)
  - Chrons (2/2), 1973 April (Box 2)
  - Chrons (1/2), 1973 May (Box 2)
  - Chrons (2/2), 1973 May (Box 2)
  - Chrons (1/2), 1973 June (Box 2)
  - Chrons (2/2), 1973 June (Box 2)
  - Chrons (1/2), 1973 July (Box 2)
  - Chrons (2/2), 1973 July (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1973 August (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 March 21-31 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 April (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 May 1-10 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 May 11-31 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 June (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 July (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 August (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 September 1-23 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 September 24-30 (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 October (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 November (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1974 December (Box 3)
- Speeches, Meetings and Testimony, 1972-1974; II
  - Power Plant Siting Conference, 1972 March 7-8 (Box 4)
  - NACOA -- Dave, 1972 August 14 (Box 4)
  - Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1972 September 11-October 17 (Box 4)
  - Brookings Meeting -- Federal Executive Institute, 1972 September 19 (Box 4)
  - UCLA Conference, 1972 October 3-5 (Box 4)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars Dinner, 1972 October 30 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1972 October 23 (Box 4)
  - UNA Meeting -- New York, 1972 November 1 (Box 4)
  - Atomic Industrial Forum -- World Energy Problems -- Nuclear Solutions, 1972 November 12-16 (Box 4)
  - Federal Statistics Users Conference, 1972 November 22 (Box 4)
  - ASME Symposium, 1972 November 29 (Box 4)
  - Atomic Energy Commission Meeting, 1972 December 1 (Box 4)
  - Leadership Conference on Energy, 1972 December 7 (Box 4)
  - Consumer Federation of America (SDF Speech), 1973 January 25 (Box 4)
  - NRECA, 1973 February 26 (Box 4)
  - George Washington University (Canfield Speech), 1973 February 27 (Box 4)
  - Meeting with Governor Lucey (Wisconsin), 1973 February 27 (Box 4)
  - IAT Evaluation Panel, 1973 March 1-2 (Box 4)
  - Brookings Seminar, 1973 March 8 (Box 4)
  - Conference on Energy Supply and Use -- Tallahassee FL, 1973 March 13 (Box 4)
  - National Wildlife Federation, 1973 March 17 (Box 4)
  - World Energy Conference -- Energy Forum, 1973 March 20 (Box 4)
  - USIA Energy Forum, 1973 March 26 (Box 4)
  - National Legislative Conference, 1973 March 30 (Box 4)
  - National Carwash Council, 1973 April 10 (Box 4)
  - Washington Journalism Center (SDF Speech), 1973 April 10 (Box 4)
  - Time Inc Conference -- Nassau, 1973 April 12-15 (Box 4)
  - Brooking Seminar, 1973 April 26 (Box 4)
  - American Medical Association Congress (speech), 1973 April 29 (Box 4)
  - Arizona Today, 1973 May 6-8 (Box 4)
  - APPA Conference, 1973 May 15 (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Public Administration, 1973 May 25 (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Public Administration Conference, 1973 May 25 (Box 4)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center Open Forum Panel, 1973 May 31 (Box 4)
  - National Governors Conference -- Lake Tahoe (SDF Speech), 1973 June 5 (Box 4)
  - Federal Executive Institute, 1973 June 12 (Box 4)
  - S. David Freeman (SDF) Testimony, New Hampshire State Hearings, Concord NH, 1973 June 12 (Box 4)
  - Japan Productivity Center -- Conference, 1973 June 19 (Box 4)
  - National Executive Institute, 1973 June 19 (Box 4)
  - Mexico -- AAAS, 1973 June 20 (Box 4)
  - Massachusetts Special Legislative Committee on Marine Boundaries and Resources -- Testimony (MC), 1973 June 21 (Box 4)
  - U.S. Jaycee's Forum -- Minnesota (SDF Speech), 1973 June 26 (Box 4)
  - American Society for Engineering Education, 1973 June 27 (Box 4)
  - United States Information Agency, 1973 July 2 (Box 4)
  - EPA Briefing, 1973 July 11 (Box 4)
  - Common Cause -- Panel Discussion (SDF), 1973 July 24 (Box 4)
  - National Legislative Conference -- Chicago IL, 1973 August 9 (Box 4)
  - Florida Energy Conference -- Tallahassee FL, 1973 August 31 (Box 4)
  - Conference for Corporate Executives, 1973 September 18 (Box 4)
  - Brookings Round Table, 1973 October 17 (Box 4)
  - School of Advanced International Studies -- Johns Hopkins University -- Washington DC, 1974 February 2 (Box 4)
  - Society for Range Management -- Tuscon AZ, 1974 February 6-7 (Box 4)
  - Wildlife Management Institute Conference, 1974 April 3 (Box 4)
  - Subcommittee on Fisheries and Wildlife Conservation and the Environment, 1974 June 11 (Box 4)
  - 1974 Summer Computer Simulation Conference -- Houston TX, 1974 July 23-26 (Box 4)
  - International Energy Policy Meeting -- Seattle WA -- Innova Corporation, 1974 August (Box 4)
  - Testimony (cancelled) -- Senate Interior Committee -- SDF, undated (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Commerce Committee -- Energy Policy Council -- SDF, 1972 August 10 (Box 5)
  - Consumers Stake in Energy Crisis -- Consumer Federation of America -- Statler-Hilton Hotel -- SDF, 1973 January 25 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Committee Government Operations -- SDF, 1973 May 1 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Foreign Relations -- SDF, 1973 May 30 (Box 5)
  - Remarks -- National Governors Conference -- Lake Tahoe NV -- SDF, 1973 June (Box 5)
  - Science and Man in the Americas Joint Conference -- SDF, 1973 June 20 (Box 5)
  - Speech -- Future of Energy -- United States Jaycees, 1973 June 26 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Commerce Committee -- SDF, 1973 July 26 (Box 5)
  - Colloquium -- Washington Center Foreign Policy -- SDF, 1973 September 18 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Commerce Committee -- SDF, 1973 November 8 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- JEC -- SDF, 1973 November 19 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Finance Committee -- SDF, 1973 November 27 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs -- SDF, 1973 November 28 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Government Operations -- SDF, 1973 December 5 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Government Operations Committee -- SDF, 1973 December 7 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Joint Economic Committee -- SDF, 1974 January 14 (Box 5)
  - Schools and the Energy Crunch -- Washington Hilton, 1974 January 17 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Commerce Committee -- Natural Gas Regulatory Bill -- Yardstick Corporation, 1974 January 22 (Box 5)
  - Statement -- Senate Interior Committee -- SDF, 1974 February 5 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Government Operations -- SDF, 1974 February 27 (Box 5)
  - Speech -- Washington Journalism Center, 1974 March 5 (Box 5)
  - American Wildlife, 1974 April 2 (Box 5)
  - Speech -- National Council of Churches -- SDF, 1974 April 30 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs, Subcommittee on Small Business -- SDF, 1974 May 1 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Joint Committee on Atomic Energy on Solar Energy Research and Development -- SDF, 1974 May 8 (Box 5)
  - Boulder, CO, 1974 May 11 (Box 5)
  - OPEC Meeting, 1974 May 14 (Box 5)
  - Science Adv. -- Piney Point, 1974 May 17-19 (Box 5)
  - Council on Foundations -- S.A., 1974 May 10 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Committe on Interior and Insular Affairs Subcommittee on Mines and Marine -- SDF, 1974 May 23 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- House Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs Subcommittee on the Environment -- SDF, 1974 June 4 (Box 5)
  - Hearings on Impacts of Rising Energy Costs on Older Americans Special Committee on Aging, 1974 September 27 (Box 5)
  - Testimony by Other Personalities, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Statement -- Council on Environmental Quality -- Monte Canfield (MC), 1973 September 13 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Senate Subcommittee on Antitrust and Monopoly -- Monte Canfield, 1973 June 28 (Box 5)
  - Testimony -- Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs -- MC, 1974 May 8 (Box 5)
  - Statement -- Senate Committee on Commerce -- MC, 1974 May 13 (Box 5)
  - SDF -- Twentieth Century Fund (book) -- Chapter IV Revised, 1974 February 5 (Box 5)
  - SDF -- Twentieth Century Fund (book) -- Twentieth Century Fund General, circa 1974 (Box 5)
  - SDF -- Twentieth Century Fund (book) -- Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
  - SDF -- World Energy Council -- Memoranda, 1972 (Box 5)
  - SDF -- World Energy Council -- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 5)
  - SDF -- World Energy Council -- Studies On, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
- Subject Files, 1972-1974; III
  - Radio/TV/Media Outreach, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - EPP Response to Policy Makers, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Final Reports Comments -- Originals, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Handbook for Grant Proposal Processing, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Study Guide -- Preliminary Draft, 1972 November (Box 6)
  - Study Guide (1/2), 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Study Guide (2/2), 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Data Resources Inc (DRI), 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Data Resources Inc -- Report -- Energy in the United States, 1974 February (Box 6)
  - Data Resources Inc -- Report -- Energy Balance Model, 1972 November 30 (Box 6)
  - Economic Integrating Model, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - Natural Resources Defense Council -- Report -- Energy Lobbying, 1973 November 1 (Box 6)
  - Natural Resources Defense Council -- Report -- Energy Policy Decisionmaking in the Federal Government, 1973 September 4 (Box 6)
  - Energy Policy Project -- Reports, 1972 August-1974 September (Box 6)
  - Scenario -- Memoranda re: Issues, proposals, etc., 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Scenarios -- General and Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7)
  - Memoranda and Scenario Papers, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Analysis of a High Energy Growth Scenario, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Scenarios -- Comments, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Scenarios, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - EEC Press Release, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Oil Spills -- Press Release, undated (Box 7)
  - Press Conference -- EEC (Box 7)
- Legal Size, 1972-1974; IV
  - AEC Reactor Development Reports -- AEC Interviews, 1972 (Box 8)
  - AEC Reactor Development Reports -- Reactor Development Structure, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Executive Office of the President -- Energy Mineral Laws, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Executive Office of the President -- Office of Emergency Preparedness, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
  - Executive Office of the President -- Office of Science and Technology, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Executive Office of the President -- White House Office, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Executive Office of the President -- Council on Environmental Quality, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Interview File (copies) -- 1971 Energy Message (Box 8)
  - Department of the Interior, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Interior Committees, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Interior Department Interviews, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
  - Congressional Contacts, 1974 (Box 9)
  - House/Senate Committee, 1974 (Box 9)
  - House of Representatives Committee on Government Operations, 1973 November 28 (Box 9)
  - House Contacts, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
  - H.U.D. Space -- Science -- Veterans Appropriations -- U.S. House of Representatives, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Report -- Cost Estimates for Scenarios, 1973 August 23 (Box 9)
  - Report -- EPP Study Guide, 1972 November (Box 9)
  - Report -- Federal Government Reorganization for Energy, 1973 August 21 (Box 9)
  - Report -- Near Term Policy Issues, 1973 August 22 (Box 9)
  - Report -- Recycle, Repair, Reuse Scenario, 1973 August (Box 9)
  - Report -- Technical Fix Scenario, 1973 August 23 (Box 9)
  - Senate Contacts, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Senator Clifford P. Hansen, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Senate Interior Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - Senate Interior Study, 1972-1974 (Box 10)
  - Joint Economic Committee, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 10)
  - Executive Contacts, 1973 (Box 10)
  - State Contacts File, 1974 (Box 10)
  - State Contacts File -- California, 1973 (Box 10)
  - State Contacts File -- Florida, 1973 (Box 10)
  - State Contacts File -- New Hampshire, 1974 (Box 10)
  - State Contacts File -- Texas, 1974 (Box 10)